Now that we know how two users can protect
data using a shared secret key, the next
既然我们知道了两个用户如何通过一个共享密钥来保护数据
question is how did these two users
generate a shared secret key to begin
接下来的问题是 这两个用户一开始如何产生一个共享密钥
with? This question will take us into the
world of public key cryptography. In this
这个问题将会把我们引入公钥密码学的领域
module, we will look at a few toy key
exchange protocols as a way to introduce
在这一单元中 为了介绍公钥密码学主要思想 我们将看到
the main ideas of public key cryptography.
We're gonna come back and talk about key
一些玩具似的密钥交换协议 我们待会儿会回来并讨论
exchange and design secure key exchange
protocols after we build a few more public
密钥交换和如何设计安全密钥交换协议 这将在我们构建了一些公钥工具之后讲到
key tools. So imagine for a second that
there a N users in the world. And the
花几秒钟设想一下 假如世界上有N个用户
question is, how do these users manage
these secret keys that they're gonna use
问题是这些用户如何管理这些密钥
to communicate with one another? So, for
example, let's assume N equals four and
以便于跟其他用户进行交流 比如 假设N=4
there are four users in the world. One
option is that basically every pair of
世界上有4个用户 一个可选方案是 每一对用户
users will share a shared secret key. And
so, for example, U1 and U3 will share a
共用一个共享密钥 所以 举例来说 U1和U3
shared, a shared secret key. I'll call it
K13. U1 and U2 will share a, a shared
共享一个密钥 我把它叫做K13 U1和U2共享一个密钥
secret key. We'll call it K12 so on and so
forth. K24 K34 and so on and so forth. K14
我们把它叫做K12 以此类推 K24 K34 等等 K14
and finally K23. The problem with this
approach is that now there are many, many
最后是K23 这种方法的问题是 现在这有很多很多
shared keys that users have to manage. And
in particular, every user has to store on
需要用户去管理的密钥 特别的 每个用户必须存储N个密钥
the order of N keys if he's gonna talk to
N other parties in this world. So the
如果他想跟世界上其他N个用户对话的话
question is can we do any better than
storing N keys per user? And the answer is
我们有没有比每个用户都存储N个密钥更好的方案 答案是有的
yes. And one way to do that is what's
called an online trusted third party. I'll
一种方法叫做在线可信第三方
use TTP to denote that trusted third
party. So the way we are going to use the
我将用TTP表示在线可信第三方 我们使用它的方法是
trusted third party is every user will now
share a single key with this trusted third
每个用户现在将与这个在线可信第三方共享一个密钥
party. So user one will share a secret
key, user two will share a secret key. And
所以用户1共享一个密钥 用户2共享一个密钥
here are our friends Alice and Bob, let's
call their secret keys k sub A and k sub B.
我们的朋友Alice和Bob在这 我们把他们的密钥叫做k_A和k_B
Okay, so now the nice thing about
this design is that now every user only
这个设计的好处就是现在么个用户
has to remember one secret key. The
question is now, what happens when Alice
只需记住一个密钥 现在问题是 当Alice
wants to talk to Bob? Somehow the two of
them have to engage in a certain protocol,
想跟Bob对话时会发生什么 他们双方必须加入一个特定的协议
such that at the end of this protocol they
will have a shared secret key KAB that the
使得在协议的最后他们会有一个共享密钥K_AB
attacker wouldn't be able to know. And so
the question is how do Alice and Bob
而攻击者无法得知 所以问题是 Alice和Bob
generate this shared secret key KAB. So
let's look at an example toy protocol for
如何产生这个共享密钥K_AB 让我们看个例子 看看能够做到这个的一个玩具似的协议
doing that. So here we have our friends
Alice and Bob. As usual Bob has his key
这里我们的朋友Alice和Bob 像往常一样Bob持有他的密钥K_B
KB, which is shared with a trusted third
party. Alice has her secret key KA,
并与可信第三方共享 Alice持有她的密钥K_A
which is also shared with a trusted third
party. So here the trusted third party
也与可信第三方共享 所以可信第三方
has both KA and KB. And the question is,
how do they generate a shared key that
持有K_A和K_B 问题是他们如何产生双方都认可的共享密钥
they both agree on, but the attacker would
have no idea what this shared key is? So
并且攻击者无法得知密钥是什么
here we're only gonna look at a toy
protocol. In particular, this protocol is
在这我们来看一个玩具似的协议 特别的 这个协议
only gonna to be secure against
eavesdropping. It's not gonna be secure
仅对窃听具有安全性 而不具有对抗
against more tampering or active attacks.
As I said, we're gonna come back and
篡改或者主动攻击的安全性 正如我说过的 我们以后会回过头来
design secure key exchange protocols later
on in the course. But for now, just to
在稍后的课程讨论设计安全密钥交换协议 但是现在只是为了
introduce this idea of key exchange, let's
look at the simplest, simplest mechanism
介绍密钥交换概念 让我们来看这个最简单的机制
that's only secure against eavesdropping.
So in other words, adversary that listens
它仅具有对抗窃听的安全性 换句话说 窃听这个会话的敌手
to the conversation won't know what
the shared key KAB is gonna be. And so the
不会知道共享密钥K_AB是什么
protocol works as follows. Alice is going
to start by sending a message to the
这个协议的工作方式如下 开始 Alice向可信第三方发送
trusted third party saying, hey I want a
secret key that's going to be shared with
一个消息说 我想要一个能够跟Bob共享的密钥
Bob. What the trusted third party will do
is it will actually go ahead and choose a
可信第三方实际上将会
random secret key, KAB. So the trusted
third party is the one who's gonna
直接选择一个随机密钥K_AB 所以可信第三方将会
generate their shared secret key. And what
it will do with this key is the following.
产生他们的共享密钥 它将会这样处理这个密钥
It's gonna send one message back to
Alice. But this message consists of, of
它将给Alice发回一个消息 这个消息包含两部分
two parts. The first part of the message
is an encryption using Alice's secret key,
消息的第一部分使用Alice的密钥加密
using the key KA, of the message this key
is supposed to be used between parties
也就是使用密钥K_A 这个密钥将在Alice和Bob之间使用
Alice and Bob, and she includes the secret
key KAB inside the message. Okay? So just
她将会把密钥K_AB包含在消息中
to be clear, what's happening here is that
the message that gets encrypted is the key
为了清晰起见 在这儿发生的是 被加密的消息是密钥
KAB plus the fact that this key is
supposed to be a shared key between Alice
K_AB和这个密钥将会是Alice和Bob的共享密钥这一事实
and Bob. Okay. And this whole message is
encrypted using Alice's secret key. The
好了 整个消息使用Alice的密钥加密
other part of the message that the TTP
sends to Alice is what's called a ticket.
TTP发给Alice的消息的另一部分叫做票据
And this ticket is basically a message
that's encrypted for Bob. So in other
这个票据基本上是为Bob加密的 换句话说
words, the ticket is gonna be an
encryption under the key KB of, again, the
票据是使用密钥K_B加密的
fact that this key is supposed to be used
between Alice and Bob. And she
表示这个密钥是在Alice和Bob之间使用的这一事实
concatenates to that the, the secret key,
KAB. Okay, so again, the message that's
然后她将其附在密钥K_AB之后 再说一遍
encrypted inside of the ticket is the fact
that this key is to be used by Alice and
票据里加密的消息是这一密钥会在Alice和Bob之间使用这一事实
Bob. And, the secret key, KAB, is included
in the ticket as well. Okay, So these two
密钥K_AB也包含在票据中 这两个消息
messages, Here, let me circle them. These
two messages are sent from the trusted
在这 让我把他们圈起来 这两个消息被可信第三方
third party to Alice. Now I should mention
that the encryption system E that is
发给Alice 现在我应该说一下 这里实际使用的加密系统E
actually being used here is a CPA secure
cipher and we'll see why that's needed in
是CPA安全密码 我们稍后会看到为什么会需要它
just a minute. So, this is the end of the
conversation between Alice and this
这就是Alice和可信第三方会话的最后部分
trusted third party. Basically as we
said at the end of this conversation,
基本上正如我们说过的 在会话的最后
Alice receives one message that's
encrypted for her and another message
Alice收到一个为她加密的消息和另外一个叫做票据的消息
called a ticket that's encrypted for Bob.
Now at a later time when Alice wants to
那是为Bob加密的 现在当Alice晚些时候想跟
communicate securely with Bob what she
will do, is of course, she will decrypt
Bob安全的对话的时候 她所要做的就是 当然 她先解密
her part of the message. In other words
she will decrypt the cipher text that was
她那部分的消息 换句话说她将解密使用密钥K_A加密
encrypted using the key KA and now she has
the key KAB. And then to Bob, she's going
的那部分密文 现在她有了密钥K_AB 然后她将对Bob发送
to send over this ticket. Bob is going
to receive the ticket and he is going to
这个票据 Bob会收到这个票据并将
use his own secret key KB to decrypt it and
then he himself will also recover the
使用他自己的密钥K_B解密它 然后他也会发现
secret key KAB. So now they have the
shared secret key KAB that they can use
密钥K_AB 所以现在他们有共享密钥K_AB 他们可以
to communicate securely with one another.
And the first question to ask is, Why is
使用它来安全地跟对方通信 第一个要问的问题是
this protocol secure? Even if we only
consider eavesdropping adversaries. So,
为什么这个协议是安全的 尽管我们只考虑在窃听的敌手
let's think about that for a minute. So,
at the moment all we care about is just
我们考虑一下这个问题 现在我们关心的只是
security against an eavesdropper, So let's
think. What does an eavesdropper see in
对抗窃听者的安全 我们想一下 一个窃听者能够在这个协议里
this protocol. Well basically he sees
these two cipher texts. Right, he sees the
发现什么 基本上他能看到这两段密文 是的 他看到
cipher text that's encrypted for Alice.
And then he sees the ticket that's
为Alice加密的密文 然后他能看到为Bob加密的
encrypted for Bob. And in fact he might
see many instances of these messages, in
票据 事实上他能看到很多这些消息的实例 特别是
particular if Alice and Bob continuously
exchange keys in this way he's gonna see
如果Alice和Bob不断地用这种方式交换密钥 这样他能看到
many messages of this type and our goal is
to say that he has no information about
很多这种消息 我们的目标是让他得不到
the exchanged key KAB. So this follows
directly from the CPA security of the
这些交换的K_AB密钥的信息 所以这是直接来自密码E D的
cipher E D because the eavesdropper can't
really distinguish between encryptions of
CPA安全 因为窃听者不能真正区分加密的
the secret key KAB from encryption of just
random junk. That's the definition of CPA
密钥K_AB和加密的随机无用信息 这就是CPA安全的定义
security and as a result, he can't
distinguish the key KAB from, you know,
作为结果来说 他不能区分密钥K_AB和
random junk which means that he learns
nothing about KAB. This is kind of a very
随机无用信息 这意味着他不能得到K_AB的任何信息 这是一种非常
high level argument for why this is
eavesdropping security but it's enough for
高水平的论点 解释了为什么它具有对抗窃听的安全性 但是对于我们的
our purposes here. So the bottom line is
that in this protocol the eavesdropper
目的来说足够了 所以底线是在这个协议中窃听者
would actually have no information about
what KAB is. And therefore it's okay to
确实不知道关于K_AB的任何信息 因此使用
use KAB as secret key to exchange messages
between Alice and Bob. Now let's think
K_AB作为密钥去实现Alice和Bob之间的信息交换是可行的 现在我们
about the TTP for a minute. So first of
all, you notice that the TTP is needed for
考虑一下TTP 首先 你会发现TTP对于每一次
every single key exchange. So basically
Alice and Bob simply cannot do key change
密钥交换都是必要的 所以基本上Alice和Bob不能更改密钥
unless the TTP is online and available to
help them do that. And the other property
除非TTP在线并且可用 另一个关于这个协议
of this protocol is in fact, the TTP knows
all the session keys. So if somehow the
的性质是 事实上TTP知道所有的会话密钥 所以一旦发生什么情况使得
TTP is corrupt, or maybe it's broken into,
then an attacker can very easily steal all
TTP损坏了 或者可能它被破坏了 攻击者就能够很容易地偷取到
the secret keys that have been exchanged
between every user of this system. This is
这个系统中所有被用于用户间交换信息的密钥 这就是
why this TTP is called the Trusted Third
Party because, essentially, it knows all
为什么这个TTP被叫做可信第三方 因为实质上 它知道所有的
the session keys that have been generated
in the system. Nevertheless the beauty of
在系统中被生成的会话密钥 然而这个机制的妙处在于
this mechanism is that it only uses
symmetric key cryptography, nothing beyond
它只用对称密钥加密 在此之外就没有
what we've already seen and as a result it is
very fast and efficient. The only issue is
超出我们所见过的东西了 而且作为结果来说它很快又很有效率 唯一的问题是
that you have to use this online trusted
party and it's not immediately clear if for
你必须使用这个在线的可信第三方 它一看上去并不是很清楚
example we wanted to use this in the
world wide web who would function as this
比如我们想使万维网作为在线可信第三方来使用它
online trusted third party. However, in a
corporate setting this might actually make
然而在企业环境中这可能实际上是有意义的
sense if you have a single company with a
single point of trust it might make sense
前提是你有一个公司和一个单点信任的系统 那么实际上指定一个机器
to actually designate a machine as a
trusted third party. And in fact a
作为可信第三方可能有意义 事实上一个
mechanism like this not quite as the way I
described it, but a mechanism like this is
像这样的机制并不十分像我刚才描述的那样 但是像这样的机制
the basis of the Kerberos system. So
this is our first example of a key
是Kerberos系统的基础 所以这是第一个例子
exchange protocol that allowed Alice and
Bob to set up shared keys, however I
关于一个允许Alice和Bob设置共享密钥的协议 然而
really want to point out that this is just
a toy protocol. Very, very simple and is
我真正想指出的是这只是个玩具似的协议 非常非常的简单
only secure against eavesdropping
attack. It's actually completely insecure
而且它仅仅对于抵御窃听攻击有效 对于抵御主动攻击者而言
against an active attacker. And here's a
very simple example of how an active
这是完全不安全的 这里有个非常简单的关于主动攻击者
attacker might destroy this protocol, and
so let's just look at replay attacks. So
如何破坏这个协议的例子 让我们就来看看重放攻击
here imagine the attacker records the
conversation between Alice and some online
想象攻击者记录了Alice和某些网商的会话
merchant. Let's call him Merchant Bob. So
for example, imagine Alice orders a book
让我们叫他商人Bob 比如 想象一下Alice从商人Bob
from the merchant Bob and the transaction
completes and Bob accepts payment for this
那里订购了一本书 交易完成后 Bob收到了这本书的款项
book. And actually sends Alice a copy
of this book. What an attacker can do now
然后给Alice寄出了这本书 现在攻击者可以做的是
is, he can complete, completely record the
conversation and simply replay the
他可以完全记录下所有会话 然后过段时间简单地将
conversation to merchant Bob at a later
time. Bob will think that Alice just
会话重放给商人Bob Bob会以为Alice是重新订了
reordered another, another copy of the
book and he'll charge her again for it,
另一本同样的书 然后他会要求她再次付款
and send her this, this copy again. So
essentially by replaying a conversation
然后寄给她这本书 所以本质上通过重放一个会话
you can cause quite a bit of harm to
Alice, and as a result this is a simple
你可以对Alice造成很大危害 作为结果来说这是一个简单的
example of why this protocol is completely
insecure against active attacks, and
例子 关于为什么这个协议对于抵御主动攻击者而言是完全不安全的
should never be used in the real world. As
I said we're going to come back in a few weeks
永远不应在现实中使用它 正如我之前说的 我们将会在几周后回来
and talk about secure versions of this
protocol, and you'll see how to make this
然后探讨一下这个协议的安全版本 然后你会知道如何让它
work, in the real world. Nevertheless, you
see that this, this very simple protocol
在现实中实现 不过 你会发现这个简单的协议
already raises a very interesting
question. And the question is, can we
已经提出了一个非常有趣的问题 这个问题是 我们可否
basically design key exchange protocols
whether they're secure against
设计一个密钥交换协议使得它不但可以抵御
eavesdropping or secure against active
attackers. The question is, can we design
窃听攻击而且还可以抵御主动攻击者 简单来说就是 我们可否设计
key exchange protocols that are secure,
but work without an online trusted third
一个安全的密钥交换协议 它不需要在线的可信第三方就能安全工作
party. So we don't wanna rely on any
online trusted party that's necessary to
我们不想依赖任何在线的可信方用于
complete the key exchange protocol. And so
the amazing answer is that in fact this is
完成我们的密钥交换协议 然而令人惊奇的答案是 这是
possible. We can do key exchange without a
trusted third party. And this is, in fact,
可能的 我们可以不借助可信第三方来交换密钥 而且它事实上
the starting point of public cryptography.
So I'm gonna show you three ideas for
是公钥密码的起点 所以我要给你们展示三个想法
making this happen and we're gonna talk
about them in much more detail in the, in
关于如何去做到它 然后我们会在接下来的单元里谈更多的细节
the coming modules. So the first idea is
actually due to Ralph Merkle back in 1974.
所以第一个想法实际上是由Ralph Merkle在1974年提出的
This was, he was, when he was just an
undergraduate student. And already he came
当时他还只是一个本科在读的学生 然而他已经
up with this really nice idea for key
exchange without an online trusted third
想到了这个极好的想法 关于如何不依赖在线可信第三方交换密钥
party. So that's one example that
we're gonna look at. Another example is
这就是我们将要看的一个例子 另一个例子是
due to Diffie and Hellman. Back in 1976
they both actually, working here at
Diffie和Hellman在1976年提出的 实际上他们都是在斯坦福大学
Stanford University, came up with this idea
that launched the world of modern key
这里工作的 他们的想法推动了现代密码学的发展
cryptography. And the third idea is due to
Rivest, Shamir and Adleman working at MIT and
第三个想法是在MIT工作的Rives、Shamir和Adleman提出的
we're going to look in detail exactly how
each of these ideas work. But I do want to
我们要详细谈谈的这些想法是如何实现的 但是我必须得说
mention that the work on public key
management hasn't stopped in the late
公钥管理系统的研究在七十年代末还没有结束
seventies. In fact there have been many
ideas over the years and here I'll just
事实上多年以来新想法层出不穷 这里我只
mention two from the last decade. One is
call identity based encryption, which is
提一下近十年来的两个想法 其中一个叫做基于身份的加密
another way for managing public keys. And
another is called functional encryption,
这是另一种管理公钥的方法 另一个叫做函数加密
which is a way of giving secret keys that
only partially decrypt a given cipher text.
由它给出的密钥 只部分地解密给定密文
And so we're gonna talk about the core of
public key crypto in this and the next week
我们在本周和下周将会谈谈公钥密码的核心
and we'll talk about these more advanced
ideas later on in the course.
然后我们将在之后的课程里谈谈这些更加先进的理念